<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eleventh collection of papers relating to the present juncture of affairs in England and Scotland</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39219</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1822</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08704338</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08704338</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41592</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39219)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41592)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1258:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Eleventh collection of papers relating to the present juncture of affairs in England and Scotland</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Richard Janeway ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Eleventh in a series of 12 collections issued in 1688-1689 under title: A collection of papers relating to the present juncture of affairs in England; and reissued in 1689 under title: A compleat collection of papers, in twelve parts, relating to the great revolutions in England and Scotland.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>(from t.p.) I. An answer to the desertion discuss'd, being a defence of the late and present proceedings -- II. Satisfaction tendred to all that pretend conscience for non-submission to our present governours, and refusing of the new oaths of fealty and allegiance -- III. Dr. Oates his petition to the Parliament, declaring his barbarous sufferings by the papists -- IV. An account of the Convention of Scotland -- V. A speech made by a member of the Convention of the Estates in Scotland -- VI. The grounds on which the Estates of Scotland declared the right of the crown of Scotland forfaulted, and the throne become vacant -- VII. The opinion of two eminent Parliament-men, justifying the lawfulness of taking oaths of allegiance to King William and Queen Mary.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Revolution of 1688 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1714 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41592:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41592:1"/>
            <p> ELEVENTH <hi rend="blackletterType">Collection of Papers</hi> Relating to the Preſent Juncture of Affairs in <hi rend="roman">England</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VIZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. An Anſwer to the Deſertion Diſcuſs'd, being a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the late and preſent Proceedings.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Satisfaction tendred to all that pretend Conſcience for Non-ſubmiſſion to our preſent Governours, and refuſing of the New Oaths of Fealty and Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> his Petition to the Parliament, declaring his barbarous Sufferings by the Papiſts.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. An Account of the Convention of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">V. A Speech made by a Member of the Convention of the Eſtates in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">VI. The Grounds on which the Eſtates of <hi>Scotland</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the Right of the Crown of <hi rend="roman">Scotland</hi> 
               <hi rend="blackletterType">Forfaulted,</hi> and the Throne become <hi rend="blackletterType">Vacant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">VII. The Opinion of two eminent Parliament-Men, juſtifying the Lawfulneſs of taking the Oaths of Allegiance to King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Janeway</hi> in Queen's-head-Court in <hi>Pater-noſter-Row,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:41592:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41592:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO THE DESERTION DISCUSS'D.</head>
            <p>IF many of our Long-Rob'd Divines, puft up with a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of their own Parts, would but keep cloſer to their Texts, and their Duties, moſt certainly our Peace and Union would be much firmer, and more aſſured then it is. For being ſway'd by Intereſt and Profit, they are more afraid of loſing the Advantages of Earthly Preferment, then the Treaſures of Heavenly Felicity. Unleſs they ſwim in their own Wiſhes and Deſires, all Things are out of Order. The Church is in danger, they cry; here are <hi>Sharers</hi> coming in among Us: And by an odd kind of Eccleſiaſtical Policy, ſeem rather inclinable to return under the Yoke of Popery, then to endure the Equality of a Diſſenting Proteſtant; rather to be at the check of a Pope's Nuncio, then ſuffer the Fraternity of a Proteſtant Nonconformiſt. They ſaid nothing to the late King, till he began to touch their Copy-holds: then they call'd out for Help; and now they are angry with their Relief, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are afraid of well they know not what. And this is their Misfortune, that if all things anſwer not the full Height of their Expectations, they are the firſt that ſhould be laſt diſſatisfied. If all things go not well, as they imagine, they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41592:3"/> preſently grow moody and waſpiſh; and while they inſinuate their empty Notions into others, who admiring the fluency of their Pulpit Language, either out of Ignorance, or Lazineſs, allow them a Prerogative over their Underſtandings, the whole Nation muſt be embroyl'd by their Surmiſes and Miſtruſts.</p>
            <p>Elſe what had that Gentleman, who wrote the <hi>Deſertion Diſcuſs'd,</hi> to do to buſy his Brains with a <hi>Subject,</hi> neither ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to his Function, nor proper for his Talent? Why ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e be ſetting himſelf up againſt the voted Judgment of the chiefeſt and greateſt part of the Kingdom? A Man of his Profeſſion would have doubtleſs better employ'd himſelf, in contemplating the Story of the <hi>Three Murmurers</hi> againſt <hi>Moſes;</hi> and there have learn'd a more ſanctifi'd Leſſon, then to exalt his Soph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtry againſt the Debates of a Solemn Aſſembly contriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Publick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſervation. For certainly never was a fairer Proſpect then now, ſince the many Revolutions under which the Britiſh Monarchy has labour'd, of its being reſtor'd to its ancient Grandeur and Renown, and of enjoying the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of Peace and Proſperity in a higher meaſure then ever. So that it muſt be look'd upon as the Effect, either of a moſt pernicious Malice, or a ſtrange diſtraction of Brain, for ſuch <hi>Diſcuſſers</hi> as theſe, to be throwing about the Darnel of their nice and froward Conceptions, on purpoſe to choak the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations of ſo glorious a Harveſt. For they muſt be Men that want the government of right Reaſon within themſelves, as being enſlav'd either to vicious Cuſtom, or partial Affection, or elſe they would never run themſelves and others with ſo much precipitancy, into the ſhame and ignominy of upholding the ſubvertors of National Conſtitutions. And all this to blacken and defame the noble Endeavours, and prudent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of thoſe renowned Patriots that purſu'd the only means to reſcue a languiſhing Monarchy from impending Thraldom and Ruin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He does not wonder,</hi> he ſays, <hi>that a Man of ſo much ſenſe and integrity as his Friend is, ſhould be ſurprized at the Thrones being declared Vacant by the Lower Houſe of Convention. For how,</hi> ſays his Friend, <hi>can the Seat of the Government be empty, while the King, who all grant, had an unqueſtionable Title, is ſtill liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> here forgot, that it had been the reſolv'd
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41592:3"/> Opinion of two Parliaments already, That there was no Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity for the Proteſtant Religion, the King's Life, or the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd Government of the Kingdom, without paſſing a Bill for diſabling the Duke of <hi>York</hi> to inherit the Imperial Crown of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and that unleſs a Bill were paſs'd for excluding the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> the Houſe could not give any Supply to the King, without Danger to his perſon, the Hazard of the Proteſtant Religion, and Breach of the Truſt in them repos'd by the People. Upon which a Bill did paſs the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and was ſent up to the Lords for their Concurrence, by which <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi> was excluded and made for ever uncapable to Inherit, Poſſeſs or Enjoy the Imperial Crown of this Realm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and he adjudg'd Guilty of High Treaſon, and to ſuffer the Pains and Penalties as in Caſe of High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, if after ſuch a Time he ſhould claim, challenge, or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to poſſeſs or exerciſe any Authority or Juriſdiction, as King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in any of the ſaid Dominions. 'Tis true, the Lords did not paſs this Bill, for Reaſons well known; yet was it ſuch a mutilation to the Duke's Title, to be diſabled from ſucceeding in the Kingdom, by the whole Body of the Commons, who are the Repreſentatives of the Nation, that it can never be ſaid, that all Men <hi>granted his Title unqueſtionable,</hi> as the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> impoſes upon the World. Beſides the many Inſtances in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, of ſeveral Princes who have forfeited their Succeſſion, and conſequently their Title to the Crown, for revolting from the Eſtabliſh'd Religion of the Realm.</p>
            <p>But, ſays the <hi>Diſcuſſer,</hi> for I look upon his Friend and Him to be all one; (and that he does but put the Queſtion with one ſide of his Mouth, and anſwer it with the other) <hi>I had thought our Laws, as well as our Religion, had been againſt the Depoſing Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That's not the Queſtion; but whether a Prince may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thoſe Miſcarriages in Government, whether he may not ſo far, <hi>peccare in Leges &amp; Rempublicam,</hi> as to incur the Forfeiture of his Regal Power? and whether a Prince may be allow'd to ſubvert the ancient Conſtitutions and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of a Nation, and yet be ſaid to be the Lawful King of that Realm? Theſe are the Queſtions: For then it is not the Law that depoſes him, nor the Religion that juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies it. But it is He that depoſes Himſelf: 'tis the bad Advice
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41592:4"/> of Evil Counſellors to which he Liſtens, and which he follows to the ruin of the Kingdom, contrary to the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Contract between Princes and People, grounded upon the Foundations of all Original Government; I ſay, 'tis that Adhering to Evil Counſel which depoſes a Prince by degrading him from a Lawful King to an Unlawful Tyrant, and renders him Liable to the Animadverſion of the Law, and the impeachments of the oppreſs'd and injur'd People. To aſſert otherwiſe were to deprive all National Law and Religion of their ſelf Defence; which is againſt all the Law and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the World. I am apt to believe that Chriſt himſelf had no very good Opinion of the lawfulneſs of <hi>Herod</hi>'s Regality, when he ſent him that Meſſage, <hi>Go tell that Fox, Herod:</hi> Which I look upon as a Depoſal and Degrading of that Arbitrary Prince by the Founder of our Religion, in his own Breaſt and Judgment, though he forbore the Execution of his Celeſtial Power. And therefore it is not the Error of Religion, but the Fault of thoſe that do not well diſtinguiſh, that Religion ſuffers in her Doctrines. For only he who governs according to Law is a King, he that endeavours to ſubvert the Law, is none. Nor is every rambling and precipitate Brain to be Judg of this neither, but the Solid Law, and fundamental Conſtitutions of the Realm. So that the Country Gentleman was miſtaken in his Thoughts, both of our Laws and our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. However the pretended Scrupulous Country Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man deſires the <hi>Diſcuſſer to expound the State-Riddle of the Vacan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and to give him the Ground of the late extraordinary Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> gives no direct anſwer at preſent, but deſires his Friend to take notice, <hi>That the Gentlemen of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, who declar'd a Vacancy in the Government, lay'd the main Streſs of their opinion upon the King's withdrawing himſelf. For that ſince the Story of the French League, and the Buſineſs of the Prince of</hi> Wales <hi>were paſs'd over in ſilence, moſt Men believed that the pretended Breach of that which they called the Original Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract was no more then a popular Flouriſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which is ſuch an imperfect peice of Incoherence, that none but a madman would have thruſt in by Head and Should<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> has done. For how can it be inferr'd that the <hi>Breach of the Original Contract,</hi> ſhould be a <hi>Popular</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:41592:4"/> 
               <hi>Flouriſh,</hi> becauſe the Clandeſtin League, and the <hi>Falſe Birth</hi> are hitherto paſs'd over in ſilence? As for the <hi>ſurreptitious Birth,</hi> one would think it was ſufficiently dilated upon in the Declaration of the Lords; and why it is not farther brought upon the Stage, there may be ſeveral Reaſons given; and among the reſt, becauſe it may be thought that the Impoſture will vaniſh of it ſelf, and ſo there will be no need of caſting an Eternal Blot upon the memory of them that contriv'd and own'd it. Then for the Clandeſtin League, it Suffices that there is apparent Proof of it in Bank. But to call the Breach of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal Contract <hi>pretended,</hi> and a <hi>Popular Flouriſh,</hi> is a yerk of Malitious Reflection, which only ſerves to expoſe the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> to Publick cenſure. For as there is nothing more certain, then that there is an Original Contract between the King and People of <hi>England,</hi> the Breach of which has coſt the Effuſion of ſo much Blood; ſo is it as certain that that Original Contract was never ſo infallibly broken then it was of late. Which as it is allow'd by all the Laws of God and Man, to be a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ground to ſeek a Remedy; ſo was nothing more vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly urg'd by the Convention. Which might have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd the <hi>Diſcuſſer,</hi> that they did not pretend it for a popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Flouriſh.</p>
            <p>But now, leſt the Country Gentleman ſhould <hi>be ſhogg'd by ſeeing the Votes of ſo conſiderable a Meeting, debated by a private Hand;</hi> the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> reminds him, <hi>That a Parliament and a Convention are two different Things. The latter, for want of the King's Writs and Concurrence, having no ſhare in the Legiſlative Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> forgets, that it was only a Convention of Lords that ſent to <hi>Richard</hi> the Second to meet them at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter;</hi> which the King at firſt promis'd to do; but upon altering his Mind, ſent him another peremptory Meſſage, that if he would not come according to his Promiſe, they would chuſe another King; and then proceeding farther, according to that Power they had, expell'd againſt the King's Will ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of his chiefeſt Favourites from the Court; conſtrain'd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to put in Sureties to appear at the next Parliament, and caus'd ſeveral others to be arreſted and committed to ſeveral Priſons. If a Convention could do this where the King was preſent, what ſignifi'd the Writs and Concurrence of an
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41592:5"/> abſent Prince. Nor did they contend for Legiſlative Power, but only met in a kind of embodied Dictatorſhip to take care of the preſent Neceſſity of Affairs.</p>
            <p>But this, ſays the Diſcuſſer, was not juſtifiable, for that <hi>the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſity which they pretended, was either of their own making, or of their own ſubmitting to, which is the ſame Thing.</hi> But this is all Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. For if the Neceſſity was of their own making, then were the Lords and Commons the Authors of all the Miſcarriages which they laid to the late King's Charge; If of their own ſubmitting to, then would they never have call'd out for ſuccour and crav'd Relief from their Oppreſſions. No—They were thoſe crying Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſum'd up in the Declaration of the Lords Spiritual and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Commons aſſembl'd at <hi>Weſtmiſter</hi> preſented to their Preſent Majeſties upon the Twelfth of February Laſt; which when the late King could not juſtify them by force of Arms, but fled for it, not being able to anſwer his endeavours to ſubvert and Extirpate the Proteſtant Religion and the Laws and Liberties of the Kingdom, put them to that neceſſity of aſſembling after an Unuſual Manner, to provide for the Common Safety.</p>
            <p>How ever the Diſcuſſer will have it a Neceſſity of their own creat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, tho never ſo falſe. <q>For, ſays he, if the King had either not bin driven out of his Dominions, or invited back upon honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Terms, they needed not have had recourſe to ſuch unuſual ſingular Methods of proceeding.</q> And thus the Diſcuſſer rambles out of one Untruth into another. For he fled from offer'd Treaty, forſook the defence of his own Forces, and left them to be disbanded in Arrears and without Payment; ſlipt from his own Council by Night, after he had appointed to meet them in Conſultation the next Morning. Nor could he juſtly ſuſpect, that any Violence would have been offer'd to Him in particular, being ſo well aſſur'd as he could not chooſe but be, of the Generous Inclination, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Reſpect which the Prince had to his Perſon. But if the Guilt of peculiar Miſcarriages haſten'd his Departure, or overſway'd him toleave the He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m of Rule without any Form or Face of Goverment: That could ne're be call'd an Expulſion out of his Dominions. And therefore when a certain Gentleman waiting on him at <hi>Fever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham</hi> beſought him to return to <hi>London,</hi> he gave the Perſon this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, <hi>That he was an honeſt Gentleman, but knew not what he knew.</hi> And when he had once abandon'd the Kingdom all forlorn without either Head or Conduct, without Council, or any Countenance of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41592:5"/> Authority, then according to the Judgment of the Common-wealth of <hi>Venice</hi> in reference to the Succeſſion of <hi>Henry</hi> the 4<hi>th.</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long'd to the Nobility and chief Perſons of the Land, as they are the chief Defence of the Royal Authority, to take care of the Publick Safety, whether by uſual or unuſual Methods of proceeding it matters not; and they have both <hi>the Authority</hi> of Law and Neceſſity to juſtify their Proceedings.</p>
            <p>As for his being <hi>invited back upon Honourable Terms,</hi> 'tis well known how he return'd back, and went through the City on the Sunday Night, attended by his own Guards, and lodg'd in <hi>White-Hall,</hi> and this moſt certainly in order to an Accommodation. Only becauſe the Prince was coming to Town, he was ſent to, and for the avoiding any Diſturbance that might be prejudicial to his Perſon, was humbly deſir'd to retire to <hi>Ham-</hi>Houſe, with Liberty to make choice of what Perſons he thought fit to attend him. Which he promiſed to do; but recollecting himſelf, and deſiring to know whether he might not return back to <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> word was ſent him the next Morning that he might do as he pleas'd. All this while here was no Conſtraint put upon him; ſo that he could not be ſaid to be driven out of his. Dominions, but that it was his own Choice to forſake it.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all this, The <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> will undertake to prove, <q>That the King before his withdrawing had ſufficient Grounds to make him apprehenſive of Danger, and therefore it could not be call'd an <hi>Abdication.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But through the whole Purſuit of his Argument, the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> moſt wretchedly miſtakes the Point, quite miſtaking the Effects for the Cauſes. For, ſays he, <q>Had not the King great Reaſon to retire to ſecure his Perſon and his Honour, when he had met with ſo many unfortunate Diſappointments, with ſo many ſurpriſing and unparallel'd Accidents? When part of the Army was revolted, and the Remainder too apparently unſerviceable; When the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had ſuch fatal and unremoveable Prejudices againſt his Service? When there were ſuch terrible Diſorders in the Kingdom, and all Places were either flaming or ready to take Fire? What ſhould a Prince do when he had ſcarce any thing left him to loſe but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but conſult his Safety, and give way to the irreſiſtable Evil?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are very great Diſappointments and evil Accidents indeed to befal a Prince. But the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> forgets to tell ye, That the Prince
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41592:6"/> brought all theſe Inconveniencies upon himſelf. The <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> tells ye that part of the Army revolted, but he omits to tell ye, that it was out of a Generous Principle, for that being Proteſtants, they would not embrue their Hands in the Blood of their Fellow. Proteſtants and Countreymen, nor be Inſtruments to enſlave the Nation. He tells ye of terrible Diſorders in the Kingdom; but does not tell ye, it was time for the People to be in Diſorder, when they ſaw ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments upon their Ancient Franchiſes, ſuch Inundations of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery flowing in upon their Conſciences, and ſuch a rapid Violence of French Thraldom tumbling in upon their Necks. He complains that all Places were either flaming or ready to take Fire, but forgets to tell you who were the Incendiaries.</p>
            <p>Theſe therefore, with ſeveral others of the ſame Nature, being the true Cauſes that drew the foreſaid Inconveniencies upon the King, it follows, that tho the Secondary Conſtraint of his withdrawing might be occaſion'd by the Effects, yet the Primary Cauſe of his withdrawing proceeded from the Firſt Cauſes which produced the Effects. Conſequently ſuch a Retiring was voluntary and not forc'd; becauſe he may be juſtly ſaid to fly from ſomething of dreaded Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, rather then purſuing Danger, from which he was always at a diſtance far enough off, but dubious what would become of him as to the Former.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> makes many other grievous Complaints to juſtify the King's Firſt withdrawing (for hitherto he is altogether upon that) but when he comes to ſum up all. <q>In ſhort, ſays he, when the Forts and Revenue were thus diſpoſed of; when the Papiſts were to be disbanded, and the Proteſtants not to be truſted; when the Nation was under ſuch general and violent Diſſatisfactions; when the King in caſe of a Rupture had nothing upon the matter but his ſingle Perſon, to oppoſe againſt the Princes Arms, and thoſe of his Subjects; when his Mortal Enemies were to ſit Judges of his Crown and Dignity, if no father; when Affairs were in this tempeſtuous Condition, to ſay that a Free and Indifferent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might be choſen, with the Relation to the King's Right as well as the People's, and that the King had no juſt viſible Cauſe to apprehend himſelf in Danger, is to out-face the Sun and trample upon the Underſtandings, and almoſt upon the Senſes of the whole Nation.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As for the Fortified Towns, it was but Reaſon that his then Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who came over to reſcue the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41592:6"/> from Arbitrary Violence and Oppreſſion, ſhould demand them to be put into his Power, well Knowing them to be then in the Hands of <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts and Cut-Throats, of whom the People ſtood in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Fear, and who were rather a Conſternation then Security to the Kingdom. And the ſame reaſon holds in Relation to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue. For all the World knows, what Vaſt Sums had been Squander'd away by the late King, when Duke, to keep off the ſitting of Parliaments, and to buy off the Members when they Sate; and when that Money was ſpent ſo much to the Detriment of the Realm, what Sollicitations were made to the French King for more, to carry on the Popiſh Cauſe and Intereſt. It was as well known how the Revenue had of late Years been Embezl'd to keep up a ſtanding Army of <hi>Iriſh</hi> Ragamuffins; as if <hi>England</hi> were now in its Turn to have been conquer'd by <hi>Ireland,</hi> as formerly <hi>Ireland</hi> had been conquer'd by <hi>England.</hi> From which fears when his preſent Majeſty had delivered the Nation, it was but reaſon that his Army ſhould be pay'd out of the Publick Stock for their happy Toyl and labour. For the Publick Revenue of all Kingdoms and States was ever Originally intended for the Preſervation, and not the Deſtruction of the People.</p>
            <p>Upon the Disbanding of the Papiſts, the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> makes a ſpecial Obſervation, <hi>That no Teſt-Acts nor any Others could barr the King from Liſting them as Common Souldiers.</hi> This perhaps may be true; that is to ſay, that a Proteſtant Prince may liſt Papiſts, and a Popiſh Prince Proteſtants, to follow him in a lawful War. But when a Popiſh Prince in a Proteſtant Nation had made his chiefeſt Levies of Popiſh Common Souldiers to over-aw his Proteſtant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and put his ſole Confidence in them for his known and open Deſigns and manifeſt Endeavors to introduce Popery into a Proteſtant Kingdom, contrary to the Law, 'twas time then to think of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding ſuch Vermin, and ridding them out of the Land. And the reaſon why the Proteſtants could not be truſted was as certain. For if the King would not truſt his Proteſtants, nay diſarm'd them, when Papiſts were both arm'd and Employ'd, what reaſon had the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants to truſt the King. And this was that which among other Things created and foſter'd thoſe <hi>General and Violent Diſſatisfact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions</hi> in the Nation. For Men have naturally a <hi>general</hi> and <hi>violent</hi> Antipathy againſt having their Throats Cut if they can help it. And therefore ſince the Kingdom by a Miraculous Providence had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd its Redemption, 'tis to be wonder'd the Diſcuſſer ſhould i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41592:7"/>
'twas ever intended that the late K. ſhould be in a Condition again to oppoſe either his own or the perſons of any others againſt the Arms of the Prince or thoſe of his own Subjects. And whereas, he ſays, that the King's Mortal Enemies were to be the Judges of his Crown and Dignity, the Diſcuſſer ſhould have done well before he had made his Reflection upon ſo many Eminent Patriots, to have conſulted <hi>Grotius, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>Par.</hi> 8. and the Example of <hi>Pauſamias</hi> King of <hi>Lacedamon</hi> there cited. Certainly there was no ſuch Impoſſibility but that a Free and Indifferent Parliament might have been choſen to deal equally between the King and the People. For tho the King perhaps might be conſcious that he could not ſo well rely upon the Kindneſs of thoſe to whom he had always had ſuch an inveterate Antipathy, yet he might have rely'd upon the Juſtice of ſo many Great and Worthy Perſonages. So that it is the Diſcuſſer himſelf who out-faces the Sun and tramples upon the Underſtandings and Senſes of the whole Nation, who makes theſe little Rhetorical Flouriſhes to palliate and obſcure the Truth, and to inſinuate among the People, as if Wrong and Injuſtice had been done, where nothing was acted but what was a due debt to Self-Preſervation. And with the ſame Brazening the Diſcuſſer out-faces the Sun, and tramples up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Senſes of the Nation, to aſſert that a Deſertion of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, after ſuch Propoſals, which were rather Aſſurances of his Safety, was no Deſertion. He had been ſafer in the Affection of the People, when all his evil Counſellers had been remov'd from about him; he had been ſafer from the Importunities of his Prieſts and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites; He had been more ſecure from running himſelf into farther danger, and ſafer in the Enjoyment of his Royal Dignity. But he who had ſo Solemnly ſworn to Eſtabliſh Popery in <hi>England</hi> or die in the Attempt, thought himſelf no where ſafe perhapps, but where he might be procuring his future Bliſs, by the Performance of his Vow.</p>
            <p>The Diſcuſſer now advances to the King's ſecond withdrawing, and puts the Queſtion, <hi>what the King had done to incar a forfeiture by his firſt Retirement?</hi> Indeed what had he not done? If the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> forgot in his Diſcuſſing Heat, the <hi>Declaration</hi> preſented to their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Majeſties would have rubb'd up his Memory. Among the reſt there was one, <hi>That he had endeavoured to Subvert and Extirpate the Proteſtant Religion, and the Laws and Liberties of the Kingdom, by raiſing and keeping a Standing Army in the Kingdom in time of Peace, without Conſent of Parliament, and quartering Souldiers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41592:7"/> to Law; and by cauſing ſeveral of his good Subjects to be Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm'd at the ſame time when Papiſts were b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th Arm'd and Employ'd.</hi> Now to what purpoſe was all this, but to Subject the Kingdom to the Tyranny of the Pope? In ſuch a caſe <hi>Barelay</hi> cited by <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>per.</hi> 10. gives this for his Opinion, <hi>Si Rex regnum alinet, aut alij Subjiciat, amitti ab eo Regnum.</hi> To which <hi>Grotius</hi> himſelf adds, <hi>Si Rex reipſa tradere regnum aut Subjicere molliatur, quin ei reſiſti in hoc poſſe non dubite. Alind eſt enim Imperium, aliud habendi modus; qui no mutetur, obſtare poteſt Populus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After all this, it cannot be imagin'd that the King returned the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time <hi>with an intention to govern;</hi> unleſs he might govern at his own will and Pleaſure as he did before. But that would not be ſuffer'd him; for they who had now avoided the Yoke ſo near putting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their Necks, would never endure it ſhould come ſo near their ſhoulders again. Therefore all the Probality in the World is on this ſide, That the King perceiving, that by taking the Goverment up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him again, he ſhould not be able to attain thoſe Ends which he had made the Buſineſs of his whole Reign, reſolv'd to relinquiſh it altogether. At which time being at liberty to go or ſtay, his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture muſt of neceſſity be accounted Voluntary, and conſequently an Abſolute <hi>Abdication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, it is impoſſible that the King could be frighted out of his Dominions, by the making of two or three Addreſſes to his then Royal Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> for it was no more than rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally he could expect would be done; more eſpecially from the <hi>City</hi> to the Perſon, who next under God had deliver'd them from their Continual fears of Fire and Sword. Nor by the denying him a little Gold to <hi>Heal</hi> with; which looks like an improbable Story of the Diſcuſſer's own framing. Theſe are Motions ſo inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for a King to forſake his Dominions, that the Diſcuſſer ſeems to have Conjur'd them up meerly to degrade the Courage of the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Monarch, and to mortify his own Diſcuſſion. But after all, the Queſtion may be fairly put, whether <hi>Withdrawing,</hi> in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of our Law, does not rather imply a Guilt, than an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of Danger, unleſs it be that of being call'd to an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, ſince the Query always propounded to the Jury is, <hi>Did he fly for't?</hi> Which indeed ought to be the Legal Determination of this Diſpute.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:41592:8"/>
            <p> However the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> goes on, and tells us, <hi>We are to obſerve, that to abdicate an Office always ſuppoſes the Conſent of him who quits.</hi> And this he affirms to be the meaning of the Word out of <hi>Saluſt, Tully, Livy</hi> and <hi>Grotius.</hi> But both the Suppoſal, and the Aſſeveration are falſe. For <hi>Conſent</hi> implies, that the Queſtion muſt be put, Whether the Perſon will Abdicate or no? Which never was put to any Abdicator in this World. Upon a forc'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation it has. But a forc'd Reſignation is no Abdication. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is that <hi>Abdicare</hi> ſignifies to <hi>renounce, forgoe,</hi> or <hi>abandon.</hi> And the Motives to this Abdication are various, and generally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing upon the Reaſon of the Perſon that Abdicates himſelf, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Condition of Affairs and the Circumſtances he is under. And therefore tho a Magiſtrate may abdicate with the conſent of others, yet he rarely does it out of a natural Inclination. Thus it cannot be imagined that <hi>Lentulus,</hi> one of the Conſpirators with <hi>Catiline,</hi> abdicated the Pretorſhip, with the Conſent of his own Will, for he was one of the moſt aſpiring Men in the Univerſe; but becauſe he found himſelf ſo obnoxious that he could hold it no longer: Thus <hi>Sylla</hi> abdicated the Dictatorſhip out of a Vain-glorious Opinion of Felicity that attended him, and to ſhew that he had ſuch an awe over the <hi>Romans,</hi> that tho he were a Private Perſon, no body durſt call him to an Account for the Cruelties he had committed. Hiſtory tells us, that <hi>Diocleſian</hi> abdicated the Empire, for madneſs that he could not have his Will of the Chriſtians. How does the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> know, but that King <hi>James</hi> abdicated the Government becauſe he could not have his Will of the Proteſtants? <hi>Charles</hi> the V<hi>th</hi> abdicated the Empire, becauſe he found his wonted Good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune had left him. <hi>Bernard Rasfield</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Munſter</hi> finding himſelf between two Grindſtones, the Perſecution of the <hi>German</hi> Prieſts, for going about to deprive them of their Concubines, and the Pope's Excommunication, if he did it not; abdicated his Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality and Biſhoprick, that he might be at quiet. Laſtly, to ſhew that Abdication does not <hi>always</hi> imply Conſent, <hi>Brutus</hi> compell'd <hi>Tarquinius Collatinus</hi> to abdicate the Conſulſhip, only becauſe his <hi>Praenomen</hi> was <hi>inviſum Civitati.</hi> And then as for what the Diſcuſſer adds out of <hi>Grotius, That a Neglect or Omiſſion in the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Government, is by no means to be interpreted a Renunciation of it;</hi> there's no Body cenſures the late King for any Omiſſion or want of Diligence in the Adminiſtration of his Government, for he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41592:8"/> was too diligent indeed; and that Diligence was the main Grievance which diſguſted the People; his Diligence to extirpate the Proteſtant Religion; his Diligence to ſubvert the Laws and Liberties of the Ringdom; and his Diligence to introduce Popery. And this Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, 'tis to be fear'd, was one of the main Cauſes of his Abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Had he omitted more, he would have had leſs reaſon to have abdicated. And therefore it is a Vanity to infer that there can be no Pretence for an <hi>Abdication,</hi> becauſe the Word, as he ſays, <hi>always,</hi> that is very rarely, or never, ſuppoſes the <hi>Conſent</hi> of <hi>him that quits.</hi> For that it is not in the Nature of Man to abdicate Empires, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, Wealth and Honours, but there muſt be ſome compulſive Reaſon within that moves them to it. When Princes find the Times and Conſtitutions of the Kingdom will not bear their Government; when Emperors grow ſtiff and ſtark with Age, and begin to feel the Laſhes of ill-Fortune; when Ambitious Aſpirers perceive they muſt take other Meaſures to compaſs their Deſigns, then they ſwallow a ſelf-denying Ordinance, and think it convenient to retire from the Cares of the World, or out of Harms way.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> ſays, <hi>We have but two Inſtances with us which look like an Abdication ſince the Conqueſt,</hi> which are in the Reigns of <hi>Edward</hi> II. and <hi>Richard</hi> II. <hi>both which were unjuſtly depos'd by their Subjects.</hi> 'Tis true, they were ſo far from looking like Abdications, that they were no Abdications at all. For both thoſe Princes being under a ſtrict Confinement, it was impoſſible for them to <hi>abdicate,</hi> unleſs they could have made their Eſcapes. Therefore they were forc'd Reſignations, and conſequently formal Depoſals. Nor had the Queen or <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> any cauſe to declare the Throne Vacant, as having already taken care to fill it themſelves: And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe Princes would have reſign'd or no, it would have ſignified little to them that were by Claim in Poſſeſſion. But the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> has overſlipp'd one Inſtance of a Perfect <hi>Abdication</hi> ſince the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, which the King would have certainly felt to his Coſt, had not the Pope and the <hi>Poictovins</hi> been his true Friends: and the Caſe was much the ſame as at this Time. For the Lords and Barons of the Realm in the Reign of King <hi>John,</hi> having often deſired the King to reſtore them their Ancient Rights and Liberties, and finding nothing but Deluſions, reſolve no longer to be abus'd but betake themſelves to Arms. The King then lying at <hi>Windſor,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41592:9"/> himſelf too weak for the Lords, thought it no good way to proceed by Force but rather by Fraud, and therefore ſends to the Lords, that if they would come to <hi>Windſor</hi> he would grant their Demands. Thither the Lords repairing, tho in a Military Manner (for they durſt not truſt the King's Word) he ſaluted them all kindly, and promis'd to give them Satisfaction in all they demanded: And to that Purpoſe in a Meadow between <hi>Stains</hi> and <hi>Windſor,</hi> call'd <hi>Running-Mead,</hi> he freely conſented to confirm their former Charters; and was content that ſome Grave Perſonages ſhould be made choice of to ſee it confirm'd. But the next Day, when it was to be done, he withdraws himſelf privately to <hi>South-Hampton,</hi> and thence to the Iſle of <hi>Wight:</hi> Where it was concluded that he ſhould ſend to the Pope, acquaint him with the Mutiny of his Lords, and require his Holineſſes help. In the mean time the King lay ſculking up and down for three Months together in Corners, that no Body knew where to find him; or which was worſe, as ſome write, roving and practiſing Pyracy upon the Neighbouring Seas.</p>
            <p>Whether the Lords and Barons did in Words declare this to be a Vacancy of the Throne, is not material to enquire. Perhaps they were not ſo curious in thoſe Days: But what they did in Deeds, amounted to the ſame as if they had done it in Words. For percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving themſelves thus eluded, they ſwore upon the Holy Altar to be reveng'd. And what Revenge that was likely to have been is eaſy to conjecture, by their ſwearing Allegiance afterwards to <hi>Lewis</hi> the French King's Son, and bearing Fealty to him till the Death of the King. Whence it may be inferr'd, That if a Prince in Hoſtility with his Subjects deſerts his Kingdom, upon any Account, They who are next to the Government are not to heſitate as King <hi>John</hi>'s Barons did, in expectation of the King's Return, but immediately to take care of the Common Safety, leſt they ſhould bring the ſame Ruin upon the Kingdom, as thoſe Barons did by their Delay.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, If the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> will not be convinc'd by what has hitherto been ſaid, Let him examine the King's own words, and try whether he can pick out any better Conſtruction out of them then that which I ſhall make.</p>
            <p>Says the late King in his Letter to the Earl of <hi>Feverſham, Things being come to that Extremity, that I have been forc'd to ſend away the</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:41592:9"/> 
               <hi>Queen, and my Son the Prince of</hi> Wales, <hi>that they might not fall into my Enemies hands, I am oblig'd to do the ſame thing, and to endeavour to ſecure my ſelf the beſt I can, &amp;c.</hi> Expreſſions of a diſponding Mind, and only full of Grief for the Diſappointment of the Popiſh Career. The King was afraid of the Queen, and his Son the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> as he calls him, and therefore deeming it convenient to ſend Them out of the way, believes himſelf oblig'd to follow them. 'Tis true, there might be ſome Reaſon perhaps for him to ſend Them away; but none to ſend away himſelf, not being under the ſame Circumſtances. For let it be Paternal or Conjugal Affection, or both together; What could be a greater Deſertion than this, for the ſake of a Wife and a Son to leave three Kingdoms at ſix and ſevens? He ſpeaks of <hi>ſecuring himſelf as well as he can,</hi> but mentions nothing of Danger; only leaves it to the Lord <hi>Feverſham</hi> and others to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Cauſes of his Fears. But certainly the apprehenſion of Danger can never excuſe a Sovereign Magiſtrate from the Deſertion of his Dominions, at the ſame time ſtriving and ſtrugling under the Pangs of the Diſſolution of Government. If ſuch a Deſertion of his Territories in that forlorn and languiſhing Condition, to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany the Tribulations of a Wife and a Son, be not a perfect Abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Territories, the Words <hi>relinquiſh, deſert, forgo, aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, abdicate,</hi> have loſt their Signification. Thus <hi>Lyſimachus</hi> in <hi>Plutarch, de ſera vindicta Dei,</hi> after he had ſurrendered his Perſon and Dominions to the <hi>Getae,</hi> for a Draught of Drink, in the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of a parching Thirſt, when he had quench'd his Thirſt cryed out, <hi>O pravum Hominem!</hi> that for ſo ſmall a Pleaſure have loſt ſo great a Kingdom. He would be thought very unfit to be the Maſter of a Ship, that ſhould throw himſelf into the Sea, when his Veſſel and Cargoe were almoſt ready to periſh. And I will appeal to the Lord of <hi>Wemm</hi> himſelf, whether if he were to try an Abdicating Prince upon this Point, with the ſame Huffing and Domineering as he did Inferiour Offenders, he would take it for a good Juſtification to ſay, I had thought, or I apprehended my Perſon to be in Danger. Rather it becomes a Prince at ſuch a time to exert his Courage, and contemn his own, when the publick Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity lies at Stake, eſpecially when the Remedy propounded was ſo eaſy as the Convoking of a Free Parliament. But to withdraw at ſuch a perillous Conjuncture from the Application of his deſir'd, nay
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41592:10"/> almoſt implor'd <hi>Aſſiſtance;</hi> What can the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> think of himſelf to deny ſo plain an <hi>Abdication?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this I take to be the Opinion of the late King's Abdication, intimated by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal aſſembled at <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> Decemb. 1688. where they are pleaſed to ſay, <hi>That they did reaſonably hope that the King having ſent forth his Proclamation and Writs for a free Parliament, they might have reſted ſecure</hi> (as doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the King might alſo have done) <hi>in that Meeting. But his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty having withdrawn himſelf,</hi> &amp;c. they did therefore <hi>unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly reſolve to apply themſelves to his Highneſs the</hi> Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> &amp;c. That is to ſay, The King having withdrawn himſelf from the Cure of the Grand Diſtempers of the Nation, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently Abdicated the Government, they reſolv'd to apply themſelves to a more Skilful, at leaſt a more Willing Phyſician. Which had the Diſcuſſer more conſiderately diſcuſs'd, when he wrote his Diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, would have ſav'd him a great deal of trouble and expence.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the Reaſons which the Diſcuſſer brings to prove that the King, before his withdrawing, had ſufficient Grounds to make him apprehenſive of Danger, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it cannot be call'd an <hi>Abdication.</hi> That which follows, being altogether grounded upon certain Statutes and Laws of the Land, to the knowledg of which the Diſcuſſer ſeems to be a great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender, is anſwer'd in a Word, That they who pronounc'd the Throne Vacant, underſtood the Latitude of their Power, and the Intent and Limits of the Laws and Statutes of this Realm to that Degree, that if nothing elſe, the Conſideration of that might have deterr'd the Diſcuſſer from the Preſumption of appearing ſo vainly and ſcandalouſly in the World. Nor would I be thought ſo impertinent to tranſgreſs the Bounds of my own Underſtanding as he has done. For indeed, to tell ye the Truth, if the Diſcuſſer ſhould come to a Trial at <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> I am afraid the Lawyers will certainly inform him that he has very much either miſtaken or miſquoted his Authors.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:41592:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SATISFACTION tendred to all that pretend Conſcience for Non-ſubmiſſion to our preſent Governours, and refuſing of the New Oaths of</hi> FEALTY <hi>and</hi> ALLEGIANCE.</head>
            <head>In a LETTER to a FRIEND, By <hi>R. B.</hi> late Rector of St. <hi>Michael Querne, London,</hi> And now Rector of <hi>Icklingham All-Saints, Suffolk.</hi>
            </head>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Cannot but admire at the Stiffneſs, not to ſay Obſtinacy of ſome, in not complying with the preſent Government, conſidering the late danger of Popery, and that an Arbitrary Power was exerciſed amongſt us by our late Rulers, in aſſerting their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing Power, by the Mercenary Judges declared to be Law.</p>
                  <p>You may remember in our late Conference upon this Subject, you pleaded in Defence of your ſelves, and others, the Obligation you lay under to the Oath of Allegiance, with your Subſcription to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> contained in the 37<hi>th</hi> Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and the Firſt Canon of the Church: but if it appear that all this is rather grounded upon Miſtake, than any ſolid Reality, I will not queſtion your ready Submiſſion.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:41592:11"/>
                  <p> Oaths I confeſs are very ſtrong Ties upon Men of Conſcience, and they are to be tenderly dealt with until that Prejudice be removed; give me leave therefore with Sobriety and Meekneſs to enquire, Whether that Oath be ſtill in Force, with the Obligation to it? if not, that Plea muſt vaniſh and diſappear.</p>
                  <p>And here firſt, let me remind you of the occaſion of impoſing the Oath of Allegiance; it was injoyn'd to diſtinguiſh betwixt Church and Court, Loyal and Diſloyal Papiſts, upon that honid <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder-Treaſon,</hi> which hath left a Stain of Villany and Cruelty upon that Religion, never to be wiped off: Read over the <hi>Anatomy</hi> of that Oath, made by K. <hi>James</hi> the Firſt in his Book of the Defence of it; And what is there in it that can ſtick upon any Proteſtant? except that Clauſe of denying all Foreign Juriſdiction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Prince, or Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate: And this you ſeem'd to hint at, when you ſaid the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was a Foreign Prince.</p>
                  <p>Will you be pleaſed in anſwer to this, to fix your Thoughts upon that of the great Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul, he is excepted that put all things under him.</hi> So here, without Queſtion, the King may diveſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of all Authority and Power, and when this is done the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ceaſeth, as if he were really Dead. The Preface to the New Oath is not an authoritative Abdication; but rather a Declaration of Matter of Fact, that the late King <hi>James</hi> hath abdicated. So that in fine the main of the Controverſy lies here, Whether the late King did abdicate? For, if he did, without all Queſtion the Obligation of all Oaths taken unto him is ceaſed. In confirmation of the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative, I ſhall endeavour to make it clear that any King may, And ſecondly, That the late King did abdicate.</p>
                  <p>That Kings may denude themſelves of their Princely Power and Sovereignty, appears from what was done by <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, Emperor of <hi>Germany,</hi> and King of <hi>Spain</hi> at the ſame time, who did abdicate both; and his Subjects took new Oaths of Fealty to other Princes. Some of thoſe Times might queſtion his Courage, but none did ever except againſt the Validity of it.</p>
                  <p>May it not ſeem ſomething unjuſt to deny this Liberty to Princes, when they find themſelves overcharged with the Weight of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to retire into a Privacy for the better enjoyment of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Peace and Quiet? But I preſume no Man will deny this <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis.</hi> It remains to prove the <hi>Theſis,</hi> That the late King did abdicate.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:41592:11"/> 1. I will not dwell upon what was done by the Metropolitan, and other Lords of the Council, upon his firſt withdrawing; they came into the City, and with the Lord Mayor ſent for the Lieutenant of the Tower, ſeize upon the Keys, diſpoſſeſs the Souldiers, place a new Garriſon there, and deſire the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> to aſſume the Regen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; Why all this, if he had not Abdicated? Upon what other ground durſt they raiſe Arms, ſeize upon his Royal Fort? Or how can they excuſe themſelves from formal Rebellion and breach of Oaths, if this be not granted, and is not unpreſidented, That Princes ſhall take up their Scepters again, when they have laid them down. But to paſs by this.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. I would willingly be reſolv'd by any Thinking Man, whoſe Judgment and Teſtimony is moſt authentick in this Particular; Whether I am to reſolve my ſelf into the Judgment of the whole Nation, in a full and clear Repreſentation in Parliament, or into the private Fancies or Opinion of a few Men? I remember what you once repli'd to this, That every Mans Conſcience is to judg for himſelf in point of Practice. But do you not know when, and by whom this Principle was exploded, whilſt ſome were proſecuted for meer Matters of Worſhip? And ſhall this be pleaded by thoſe Men who ſo vigorouſly have acted againſt it, when in its own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it is ſo deſtructive of the Civil Peace? <hi>A Line and a Line is an Abomination.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Did ever any Government upon the Pretence of Conſcience diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with Diſobedience in Things neceſſary to its Eſtabliſhment? And can any Man expect to be excus'd from taking the Oaths, which is the only Moral Security the Government can expect or require; and upon this very Pretence, which if allowed, all Kingdoms muſt diſſolve into Anarchy and Confuſion; Religion and Conſcience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Common Pretentions of all Male-Contents. This may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to ſatisfy any ſober Rational Man, that is not reſolv'd to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Concluſion, be the Premiſes never ſo weak.</p>
                  <p>Some there are that preſume their Subſcription to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in her Book of Articles, will not permit them to yield their Obedience to theſe Alterations. But if this ſhall prove a Miſtake, and our Obedience ſhall be conformable to our Principles, will it not rather be eſteemed Peeviſhneſs than Conſcience?</p>
                  <p>To diſcover the Miſtake, let us conſider when, and by whom, the Articles were compoſed; and refer the Practices of thoſe Times to the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41592:12"/> Articles, as an authentick and clear Interpretation of them, and this alſo will vaniſh like Smoak.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Articles were made, or at leaſt confirmed, in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who was a conſtant aſſerter and maintainer of this Maxim, That it is lawful for a neighbouring Prince to relieve and defend the Subjects of another, when invaded in their Laws, Liberties, and Religion. Who was it that protected and aſſiſted the <hi>Hugonets</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> againſt the Tyranny and Violence of their Princes? Was it not this Gracious and Heroick Queen? And who was it that protected the <hi>Netherlands</hi> againſt the Violence and Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Monarch? And was all this contrary to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowed Doctrines of our Church, of which ſhe was the Defender? Was not this defended, or at leaſt allowed of, by the Church-Men of thoſe Times? muſt it be now inconſiſtent with the Principles of our Times? Do they bind our Hands, ſo that if we are invaded we may not crave the like Protection? Let any ſober ſcrupulous diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Perſon give a ſober Anſwer and Reſolution to theſe <hi>Queries.</hi> The <hi>Dutch Netherlands</hi> erected a new Model of Goverment under her Protection, after they had ſhaken off the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Yoak.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Let it be granted, what ought not to be denied, That the late King did abdicate, and that the Government did devolve upon the People, and theſe in a full Repreſentative of the whole Nation, whether in Parliament, or in a Convention, (it matters not which, whilſt that was a free and fair Choice) have conſtituted theſe to be our Governours; Are we not to pay and ſwear Obedience unto them, as well as their Predeceſſors? And if this were rightly weigh'd, would anſwer an Objection from that Declaration, in the Act of Uniformity, <hi>I abhor that Traiterous Poſition, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If after all this Men will fix all upon a <hi>Jus divinum,</hi> and fly to Scriptures, let them give plain poſitive Texts, for a general Form, with Rules univerſally relating unto, and obliging all Places and Men. If they cannot, let them confeſs that God hath left all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and People, to be ruled by that Government and thoſe Laws, which are moſt ſuitable to the Conſtitution and Temperament of the People; and this I lay down for a Foundation not to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown. But to Anſwer: thoſe places which are ſo much inſiſted upon, that of our Saviour's, St <hi>Paul</hi>'s, and St <hi>Peter</hi>'s, we need to make uſe of that abſurd Aſſertion of ſome of the Romaniſts, That this was only enjoyn'd and to be performed until they had oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to make a Reſiſtance.</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:41592:12"/>
                  <p> This would ſtain the Glory of the Primitive Martyrs. Not a forced, but a voluntary Martyrdom deſerves the Crown; however this gives a taſte of the Loyalty of theſe Men and their Religion, to the maintaining of which the Popiſh Princes ſacrifice all their Power and Policy.</p>
                  <p>But for a more Subſtantial Anſwer, by way of Satisfaction to theſe Scruples, let it be duly conſidered, that the Primitive Chriſtians and we were under different and diſtinct Adminiſtrations; they liv'd under abſolute Monarchs, their Grandeur was won by the Sword, and confirm'd by a pure Deſpotick Power; and therefore their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance had been unlawful, contrary to the Rule and Force of their Government: but it is quite otherwiſe with us. We are ſetled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a <hi>Gothick</hi> Model, our Princes make no Laws without our own Conſent; they are obliged to the excution of Laws made by our ſelves with their Conſent; they have no Power to diſpenſe with the breach of them by others, nor to invade them themſelves. This was own'd by the ſeven Biſhops, declar'd by former Parliaments; ſo that no Man is bound to pay their Allegiance any further; Let <hi>Caeſar</hi> have what is <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s, and the Subjects what is theirs, their Laws, their Birth-right. In ſome caſes Moral poſitive Duties are ſuperſeded by what is naturally Moral, as in the Duties of the fourth Command, ſo here. Tho Government in general be founded upon Nature, yet this or that Form is but poſitive; and if it be not conſiſtant with the end of Government, Self-preſervation, Why ſhould not it be either altered, or fixed in thoſe who will proſecute the right end, the Preſervation of the publick Peace and Liberties of the People?</p>
                  <p>To what hath been ſaid, let me add, <hi>ex abundanti,</hi> the late King's retiring into <hi>France;</hi> if it amount not to an Abdication, it comes near unto a Forfeiture, and no Prince or State can have leſs Reaſon to indeavour to reſtore him to his Crown and Dignity, than that Monarch. Whence hath he his Claim but from <hi>Hugh Capet,</hi> and he from the Election of the great Men of the Kingdom? and why did they pretend to lay aſide <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> whoſe Right it was by Succeſſion, but meerly upon this ground, He had joyned himſelf to the Enemies of the Kingdom? and ſo they transfer the Crown unto another Family, that of the <hi>Capets.</hi> And does not all Chriſtendom in general, and the Engliſh Nation in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, look upon that great Man of <hi>France</hi> as a Common Enemy? ſhall not that which may hinder Succeſſion, juſtify in part a tranſlat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41592:13"/> of it unto another? But (bleſſed be God) all theſe are cleared in an Abdication, and that aſſerted by the Repreſentative Body of the whole Nation.</p>
                  <p>And now, good Sir, be perſwaded to lay aſide all Prejudice, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your Sentiments to the Judgment of your Superiors, yield your Obedience and Fealty in taking the Oaths; this you ſee is your Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and not only ſo, but your Intereſt. It is not long ſince we were apprehenſive of Popery, and the Church-of<hi>-England-</hi>Men did ſet themſelves in direct Oppoſition againſt it, and all the Acceſſes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward it; for which the Generations to come ſhall call them bleſſed. But whence come theſe Apprenſions to be leſſened? can we expect a perfect Freedom from theſe Fears, ſhould he be re-admitted to his Authority? It is not poſſible a Popiſh Soveraign ſhould keep Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe with his Heretical Subjects, as they ſtile us; their words and Oaths, if Roman Catholicks, bind no further then ſtands with the Intereſt of their Religion, and we know who both can, and will diſpence with Oaths and Promiſes made to Hereticks.</p>
                  <p>Would you ſetter him by Laws? theſe have been, like <hi>Sampſons</hi> Cords, eaſily broken: Would you place him under Tutors and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours? He is no <hi>minor,</hi> cannot ſubmit; <hi>aut Caeſar, aut Nullus.</hi> Men are but Men at the beſt, and Time, and Preferment may alter their Judgments. However theſe would make him a Priſoner, and no King. Should we ſubmit in hopes of another Opportunity; Would he not ſettle a Correſpondence with Male-contents at Home, and Foreign Princes Abroad? and if he proſper in the Deſign, hath that Common plea, That his Promiſes are Void, becauſe made by him when under Reſtraint? And then, What will become of all that is dear unto us, Religion, Lives, Liberties, and Eſtates? This is prevented by an Abdication; ſo that if he return, it muſt be by Conqueſt, and then he will rule by the Sword, we ſhall all be in the ſame Condition, lie under the charge of Hereticks, Rebels and Traytors; the Government chang'd from a regulated Monarchy into an abſolute Tyranny, our Religion abrogated; we ſhall be ſold as Slaves, or burnt as Hereticks. If Men love Bonds and Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Rapine and Sequeſtration, Racks and Tortures, Fire and Faggots, let them continue this Humor and Averſation; but if none of theſe be lovely, as indeed they are not, let us bleſs God who hath redeemed us from the Hand of our Enemies, and the Hand of all that hate us. Let us joyn iſſue with the Divine Providence (which
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41592:13"/> hath delivered us from all theſe Evils) in ſubmitting and yielding our Obedience to our Soveraign Lord and Lady, by whoſe Conduct and Courage we are brought into a ſtate of Freedom and Peace. Be not affrighted out of this by the falſe Rumors and Reports, ſpread abroad by evil-minded Men, but let us unite in our Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to our preſent Rulers that thereby we may ſtrengthen their Hearts and Hands in our common Defence.</p>
                  <p>There remains one Prejudice, but no Objection ariſing from the vain Fears of ſome Men, that the Church begins to be ſhaken in her Authority, whilſt matters of Religion fall under a Diſpute, and no Convocation conſulted with. But this, if fully conſidered, would ſwell a private Letter into too great a Bulk. Let me for the preſent deſire you to conſider, there is nothing deſign'd in Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, but meer Matters of Ceremony, and a relaxation of ſome Laws, not conſiſtent with the greateſt Intereſt of the Nation in this preſent Juncture, the Union of Proteſtants. And out of experience, that the ſeverity of thoſe Laws never reclaim'd one Diſſenter, but rather did drive others out of the Pale of the Church; it is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of, but highly becoming the Wiſdom of thoſe worthy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triots to find out a Method, whereby all Proteſtants of every Form may be brought into an eaſy Condition. This Subject, if this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter find a candid Reception, may be more fully conſidered of, by</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your very Friend, Servant, and Brother. R. B.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:41592:14"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable the Lords Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Temporal, And to the Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ourable the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes in this preſent PARLIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT Aſſembled; The Humble tition of <hi>TITUS OATES,</hi> D. D.</head>
            <p>Moſt Humbly ſheweth,</p>
            <p>THat your Petitioner in the Year 1678, diſcovered a horrid Popiſh Conſpiracy for the Deſtruction of the late King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, His Preſent Majeſty, and the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion</hi> within theſe Kingdoms; and prov'd it ſo fully, that ſeveral Parliaments, and Courts of Juſtice, before whom he gave his Teſtimony, declared their Belief of it by publick Votes, and the Condemnation of ſeveral of the Conſpirators. For which Reaſon, and becauſe your Petitioner would not be terrified by their Threats, nor ſeduced by their Promiſes of great Rewards (with both which Temptations they often aſſulted him) to deſiſt in his Diſcovery; the Jeſuits and Papiſts purſued him with an implacable Malice, and endeavoured to take away his Fame and Life, by ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borning Witneſſes to accuſe him of Capital Crimes: but being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated in that Villanous Attempt, they firſt procured King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second to withdraw that Protection and Subſiſtence his Majeſty had, at the Requeſt of ſeveral Parliaments, allowed to your Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner; and then inſtigated his Royal Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York</hi> to proſecute your Petitioner in an Action of <hi>Scandalum Magnatum,</hi> for ſpeaking this notorious Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> That he <hi>the ſaid Duke of York was reconciled to the Church of Rome;</hi> and that <hi>It is High Treaſon to be ſo reconciled:</hi> wherein a Verdict and Judgment for
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:41592:14"/> one Hundred Thouſand Pounds Damages were obtained againſt your Petitioner, and your Petitioner was committed to the King's Bench-Priſon.</p>
            <p>After this, the ſame Popiſh Party obtained leave from King <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, to prefer two ſeveral Indictments againſt your Petitioner, for two pretended Perjuries in his Evidence concerning the ſaid Conſpiracy, which they brought on to Tryal in the Reign of King <hi>James</hi> the ſecond; and your Petitioner was upon the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of thoſe very Witneſſes, who had confronted him in three former Tryals, and were disbelieved; and through the Partial Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of the Chief Juſtice <hi>Jeffreys,</hi> in brow-beating his Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and miſleading the Juries, convicted of the ſaid Pretended Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, and received this inhumane and unparallel'd Sentence follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>viz. [To pay two thouſand Marks to the King: To be deveſted of his Canonical Habit: To be brought into</hi> Weſtminſter-Hall <hi>with a Paper upon his Head, with this Inſcription,</hi> Titus Oates <hi>convicted upon full Evidence of two horrid Perjuries: To ſtand in and upon the Pillory two ſeveral days, for the ſpace of an Hour: To be whip'd by the comman Hang-man, from</hi> Aldgate <hi>to</hi> Newgate <hi>on Wedneſday, and to be whip'd again on the Friday following from</hi> Newgate <hi>to</hi> Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn: <hi>To ſtand in and upon the Pillory five times in every Year of his Life; and to remain a Priſoner during his Life.</hi>] Which Sentence being intended, as your Petitioner hath juſt reaſon to believe, to murther him, was accordingly executed with all the Circumſtances of Barbarity; he having ſuffered ſome thouſands of Stripes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he was put to unſpeakable Tortures, and lay ten Weeks under the Surgeons Hands. Neither did their Cruelty ceaſe here, but becauſe your Petitioner, by God's Mercy miraculouſly ſupporting him, (and the extraordinary Skill of a Judicious Chirurgion) outlived that Bloody Uſage, ſome of them afterwards got into your Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner's Chamber whilſt he was weak in his Bed, and attempted to pull off the Plaiſters apply'd to cure his Back, and threatned to deſtroy him: And that nothing within their Power or Malice might be wanting to compleat your Petitioner's Miſery, they procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to be loaded with Irons of exceſſive Weight for a whole Year, without any Intermiſſion, even when his Legs were ſwoln with the Gout; and to be ſhut up in the Dungeon, or Hole of the Priſon, whereby he became impair'd in his Limbs, and contracted Convulſion Fits, and other Diſtempers, to the great Hazard of his Life. All which illegal Proceedings, and barbarous Inhumanities,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41592:15"/> your Petitioner humbly conceives were not only intended as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge upon him, but likewiſe to caſt a Reproach upon the Wiſdom and Honour of four ſucceſſive Parliaments who had given him Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, and upon the Publick Juſtice of the Nation. And your Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner humbly hopes that ſince the Papiſts themſelves have verified and confirmed his Evidence by their late open and avowed Violations of our Religion, Laws, and Liberties, this Honourable Houſe will vindicate the Proceedings of former Parliaments, and diſcharge your Petitioner from thoſe Arbitrary and Scandalous Judgments, and the unjuſt Impriſonment he lies under.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Petitioner doth therefore moſt humbly beſeech your Lordſhips and your Honours, to take his deplorable Caſe into your generous and tender Conſideration, and to give him ſuch Redreſs therein as to your Lordſhips and your Honours great Wiſdom, Juſtice, and Goodneſs, ſhall ſeem meet: <hi>And your Petitioner ſhall ever pray,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:41592:15"/>
            <head>An Account of the Convention of <hi>SCOTLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Convention of <hi>Scotland</hi> met the 14<hi>th</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1685, in Obedience to the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Lette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>; They choice the Duke of <hi>Hamilton</hi> their Preſident, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fter which they had ſeveral Debates about the Duke of <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>don,</hi> a Papiſt, who keeps the Caſtle notwithſtanding many offers of Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render, does ſtill keep it for King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They read a Letter from the King of <hi>England,</hi> in which he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts them to lay aſide all Animoſities, and Factions, and mind the Publick Good in ſecuring the Proteſtant Religion, and the ancient Laws and Liberties of the Kingdom on ſure and laſting Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, particularly that they would endeavour a Union between both Kingdoms, as one of the beſt Means for the Happineſs of both, eſpecially at this time, when the common Enemy is reſtleſs to procure the ruine of <hi>Britain,</hi> and the Proteſtant Religion every-where.</p>
            <p>After which a Letter was read from King <hi>James,</hi> requiring them to ſupport his Royal Authority, by many Threats and Promiſes, which made no Impreſſion on them; but after ſome time they drew up, and ſent a Letter to King <hi>William,</hi> full of dutiful Reſpects, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing to do that which may be acceptable to him, and ſuitable to the <hi>Genius</hi> of the Nation.</p>
            <p>After ſetling the Militia and other State-Matters, and having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved the Power into themſelves; they appointed a Commitee of 24, made up of all the Eſtates, to ſettle the Government: Which Commitee have provided for the full Meeting of the Convention Grounds and Reaſons on which they have declared the Throne Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:41592:16"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A SPEECH made by a Member of the Convention of the States in</hi> SCOTLAND.</head>
            <p>WE are now called together by his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> to Conſult and Deliberate, what Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods will be moſt proper to ſecure Our <hi>Religion, Laws</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> in order to which, the firſt thing that will fall under our Conſideration, is the ſetling the <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I take for granted that you are fully convinced, that King <hi>James</hi> the Seventh, by his many Violations of the Fundamental Laws, by his endeavouring to eſtabliſh a <hi>Deſpotick</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> and introduce <hi>Popery,</hi> (tho he himſelf had confirmed all the Laws that were enacted in Favour of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion)</hi> has thereby ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted the <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> and (that our Miſeries might have no Redreſs from him) has left us in a time when we needed his Protection moſt. The Eyes of all <hi>Europe</hi> are upon us, and it is in our Power to make our <hi>Selves,</hi> and our <hi>Poſterity</hi> either <hi>Happy</hi> or <hi>Miſerable,</hi> by making a choice, either to call back the ſame King <hi>James,</hi> and hazard once more all that <hi>Men account dear,</hi> to his Mercy; or to ſettle the <hi>Government</hi> on ſome other, under whom we may live Quiet and Peaceable Lives, without the perpetual Terror of being ſwallowed up by <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Government,</hi> which all good Men hoped were now baniſhed, and yet behold a new <hi>Off-ſpring</hi> is ſprung up, which plead eagerly for both, tho under the miſtaken Names of <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Allegiance:</hi> It's ſtrange that any Man can ſo far <hi>degenerate,</hi> as to prefer <hi>Slavery</hi> to <hi>Liberty,</hi> and that they ſhould be ſo much in love with <hi>Chains,</hi> that when they were fairly ſhaken off, they ſhould run ſuriouſly to be <hi>Fettered</hi> again; as if the <hi>Ottoman</hi> and <hi>French Government</hi> were ſo charming in our Country, that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not live without it, tho we have ſo lately groaned under the diſmal
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41592:16"/> Burden of it: And it might have been ſuppoſed that even theſe, who had been <hi>Inſtrumental</hi> in <hi>Enſlaving</hi> their <hi>Fellow-Brethren,</hi> and were grown Fat with Sucking the <hi>Nations Blood,</hi> would have taken another Method to Reconcile themſelves, than by perſuading us to purchaſe <hi>their</hi> Safety, at ſo vaſt an Expence as the <hi>Ruin</hi> of more than three Parts of the Nation will neceſſarily amount to.</p>
            <p>If we do but a little reflect on the <hi>Motives</hi> which theſe Men (blinded by Self-Intereſt) make uſe of, to delude the Nation into a Security that wanted very little of proving Fatal to it, and compare them with the ſtrong Reaſons, we have to diſſwade us from being ſo impoſed on, they will be found ſo <hi>Weak</hi> and <hi>Impertinent,</hi> that we muſt judg it next to <hi>Impoſſibility,</hi> to ſuffer our ſelves to be <hi>twice De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</hi> But if the Experience of our former Miſeries, ſo lately hanging over our Heads, (the very Thoughts of renewing which, make all good Men to tremble) has not made us <hi>Wiſer,</hi> and be not of <hi>Efficacy</hi> enough, to deter us from venturing another <hi>Shipwrack,</hi> and expoſing all again to the <hi>Diſcretion</hi> of <hi>Roman Catholicks:</hi> It's more than probable that GOD has abandoned us, <hi>and given us up to believe ſtrong Deluſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Thay will endeavour to perſwade us, that Kings are eximed from <hi>Puniſhments</hi> here on <hi>Earth,</hi> and nothing they do can be quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled by their Subjects, which indeed might with ſome Reaſon be urged among the <hi>Turks,</hi> who reſerve nothing from the Power of their <hi>Sultans,</hi> and where it's Death to diſpute his <hi>Commands,</hi> tho never ſo <hi>Arbitrary</hi> and <hi>Tyrannical:</hi> But with what Impudence can ſuch <hi>Stuff</hi> be impoſed on us, who never admit our <hi>Kings</hi> to the <hi>Government,</hi> till they ſwear to rule us according to <hi>Law,</hi> and no otherways? The <hi>Laws</hi> are the only Security we have for our Lives and Properties, which if our <hi>Sovereign</hi> ſubvert, <hi>Subjects</hi> cannot be blamed, for making uſe of the ordinary means to preſerve them, and ſince that cannot be done without withdrawing Obedience from ſuch a <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> as goes about to deſtroy them, ſuch an Act cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be ſaid to puniſh him, (becauſe we take nothing from him to which he has a juſt Claim, but do only ſhun the occaſion of making our ſelves miſerable. The <hi>Speculative Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> has done too much miſchief among us, and what has befallen the <hi>King</hi> may be juſtly imputed to it, for the believing that without Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition he might <hi>do what he pleaſed,</hi> encouraged him to take ſuch meaſures as have drawn all theſe Misfortunes on him.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:41592:17"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Others are ſo Fond as to believe, that we may be Secure in calling the King back, provided they ſo Limit him, that it will not be in his power to hurt us. Theſe Men do not conſider, how ſmall a Complement this is to a Man of the <hi>Kings Temper,</hi> from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> an <hi>Abſolute Prince,</hi> as he was pleaſed to fancy himſelf, to content himſelf with the bare Title of a <hi>King;</hi> and how inſupportable the Charge muſt be, if from being <hi>Maſter of all,</hi> he muſt force him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to comply with a thouſand <hi>Maſters,</hi> and ſee his <hi>Throne</hi> become his <hi>Priſon.</hi> But how airy is it to fancy, that any Reſtrictions of our Contrivance can bind the King? For 1<hi>ſt,</hi> It's moſt certain they can never be Voluntary, and what is conſtrained and done by Force, is by <hi>Law</hi> declared to be Void and Null; to whoſe Aſſiſtance the <hi>Pope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Diſpenſing Power</hi> being joined, would quickly blow off theſe <hi>Sampſon Cords,</hi> and the <hi>Royal Power</hi> would again revive with all its Vigour and Luſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The <hi>King</hi> is of a Religion that has in a famous Council decreed, That no Faith is to be kept with <hi>Hereticks,</hi> much leſs with Subjects whom he looks upon as ſo many <hi>Rebels,</hi> and will not miſs to treat them as ſuch, whenever they give him the Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of doing it; for his greateſt Admirers do not run to that height <hi>Idolatry,</hi> to imagine him ſo much <hi>Angel,</hi> as not to take all methods to revenge ſo great an Affront, and ſecure himſelf at our Goſt from ſuch a Treatment for the future; the apprehenſions of which Reſentments will ſtrike ſuch terrour in Mens minds, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will be capable to divert them from offering up All for an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement, and <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery</hi> will be thought a good Bargain, if they can but ſave their Lives. Then we may lament our Miſeries, but it will not be in our power to help them; for a <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Orange</hi> is not always ready to reſcue us, with ſuch vaſt Expence and ſo great hazard to his Perſon; and if our Madneſs hurry us ſo far, we deſerve rather is pity than his reſentment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> What Arguments has the King given ſince he left us, to perſuade us he will be more faithful in obſerving his Words and Oaths, than hitherto he has been? Does he not in a Letter lately printed here, expreſly ſay he has ruled ſo, as to give no occaſion of complaint to any of his Subjects? Is not the ſame Letter ſigned by one who ſacrificed both <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> to <hi>Intereſt,</hi> whoſe pernicious and headſtrong <hi>Counſels</hi> has poſted him to his Ruine, tho' all that has been done cannot make Him ſenſible of it? Sure the re<hi>-Hereticks</hi> to the See of <hi>Rome</hi> is not leſs Meritorious than before, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:41592:17"/> King <hi>James</hi> the Seventh, by breathing the <hi>French Air,</hi> become leſs <hi>Bigot:</hi> It were a Dream to fancy it. For ſo long as the <hi>Vatican</hi> thunders Excommunications againſt all ſuch as do not uſe their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endeavours to extirpate <hi>Hereſie,</hi> a <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> muſt have no Religion at all, if they be not terrible to him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>fourth</hi> Argument they made uſe of to perſuade ſuch as are and ſhall be choſen Members of the <hi>Convention,</hi> That their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to call back the King, is, That the Peace and Happineſs of the Nation cannot be otherwiſe ſecured, nor Factions or Diviſions ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed. But what Factions do you obſerve, but ſuch as they themſelves do foment, on purpoſe to diſturb our Harmony? all which would immediately die, if the Government were once ſetled on thoſe who deſerved it beſt: for then, if theſe Fops continued ſtill fond of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Tyranny,</hi> they would be chaſtiſed, as Diſturbers of the Publick Peace. The Argument may very juſtly be retorted; for if the King return, we will burſt out into a flame; and <hi>England,</hi> which has already declared, will quickly be on our Top, an Enemy too Potent and too Numerous for us, tho' we were all united, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Danger to which ſuch a Procedure will expoſe us, we cut off all hopes of an Union with that Nation, and thereby deprive our ſelves of an unſpeakable Advantage, which would redound to all ſorts of People, and would be the only means to ſupport an impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſh'd and ſinking Nation. Neither is this the only Inconveniency, tho' it be a very great one; for if we ſtate our ſelves in oppoſition to <hi>England,</hi> by <hi>Reſtoring</hi> the <hi>King</hi> whom they <hi>Rejected,</hi> it is not to be doubted but he will uſe his uttmoſt endeavour to recover that Kingdom, the loſs of which is ſo conſiderable. Now, ſeeing it were vain to ſuppoſe that the <hi>Scots</hi> alone were able to ſecond his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, he muſt needs have recourſe to the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> whoſe Religion will procure a more intire Confidence than His Majeſty can repoſe in any others. Theſe therefore muſt be received into our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom; and becauſe <hi>Scotland</hi> is the moſt proper place for Invading <hi>England,</hi> it muſt be the Scene of all the Blood and Confuſion that this melancholly Thought gives us a Proſpect of. And what treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can ſuch <hi>Sham-Proteſtants</hi> expect from theſe, who otherwiſe would have become their Friends and Allies? And what Figure will they pretend to make, when they ſet up for a ſeparate Intereſt from all the <hi>Confederate Proteſtants</hi> in the World beſides?</p>
            <p>The happy Succeſs the PRINCE his Enterprize has met with, has made a conſiderable Alteration in the Affairs of <hi>Europe;</hi> for that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41592:18"/> great Enemy of the Proteſtants, and even of Chriſtianity it ſelf, who had propos'd nothing leſs to himſelf than an Univerſal <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> whom the Stricteſt <hi>Leagues</hi> and <hi>Contracts</hi> cannot bind, but without regard to GOD or Man, threatens all his <hi>Neighbours</hi> with utter Deſtruction; by the <hi>Scene</hi>'s being changed among us, is ſo far humbled, that from a <hi>Proud</hi> and <hi>Inſulting Enemy,</hi> he is become a Supplicant for Peace; well foreſeeing, that if <hi>Britain</hi> join with thoſe other <hi>Princes,</hi> whom his Inſolence, Cruelty, and Avarice, has ſo juſtly Armed againſt him, his Ruine is <hi>Inevitable:</hi> So that if we have not <hi>Soul</hi> enough to enjoy this great <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> and can eaſily part with the <hi>Glory</hi> of being once more the <hi>Arbiters</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> let us at leaſt have ſo much <hi>Chriſtian Love</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> for the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring <hi>Nations</hi> of our own Perſwaſion, as not to expoſe them to a neceſſary <hi>Participation</hi> of theſe <hi>Plagues,</hi> which our <hi>Common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> are preparing for us, and which will certainly <hi>Terminate</hi> in all our Deſtructions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> I beſeech you to conſider what <hi>Perſons</hi> they are who would <hi>Inſtill</hi> this <hi>Poyſon</hi> in you, and you will find them of three kinds. Firſt, thoſe who <hi>Poſtponing the Common Good</hi> of the <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> are wholly acted by <hi>Self-Intereſt,</hi> conſidering that in a <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> where <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> equally Flouriſh, <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Merit,</hi> not <hi>Villany,</hi> will be rewarded. Secondly, They who are ignorant of the Nature of Government, and were never at the pains to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form themſelves what Meaſures the Law of Nature and Nations have ſet to mens Obedience, but are angry at every thing that thwarts their wild Notions, and will admit of nothing, tho never ſo reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and convincing, if their dull Capacities cannot reach it. The third ſort are ſuch as have been inſtrumental in the inſlaving their Country, and are afraid if they be called to an Account, they may be brought to ſuffer <hi>Condign Puniſhment;</hi> if ſuch cannot ſucceed in their Deſign, they at leaſt hope to be overlook'd in a <hi>General Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> ſo they have nothing uneſſayed that may tend to their own ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and if <hi>Heaven</hi> fail them, they ſummon <hi>Hell</hi> to their Aid; not that <hi>Love</hi> to their <hi>Prince,</hi> but meer <hi>Ambition</hi> and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> drives theſe <hi>Criminals</hi> to ſuch Attempts; neither are they much to blame, if they are at ſuch pains to ſow Diviſions among us. But no Perſon of <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Judgment,</hi> nor any Good Man that is truly <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> and minds the good of his <hi>Country,</hi> will ſuffer himſelf to be ſo groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impoſed on by ſuch <hi>Firebands,</hi> who would build their Furture <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary Greatneſs</hi> on the Ruine of <hi>Our Religion, Laws,</hi> and <hi>Country.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="justification">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:41592:18"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Grounds upon which the Eſtates of</hi> Scotland <hi>Declared the Right of the Crown of</hi> Scotland FORFAULTED, <hi>and the Throne become</hi> VACANT.</head>
            <p n="1">I. BBcauſe King <hi>James</hi> the Seventh is a Profeſſed Papiſt.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That the ſaid King <hi>James</hi> did aſſume the Royal Power, and acted as King without ever taking the <hi>Oath</hi> required by Law.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That he hath by the Council of evil Men invaded the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Conſtitution of the Kingdom, and changed it from a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited Monarchy to an Abſolute and Deſpotick Power.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Which Power he hath imployed to the Subverſion of the Proteſtant Religion, and the Violation of the Rights of the Subject. And thereby,</p>
            <p n="5">V. Hath inverted all the Ends of Government.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="opinion">
            <head>
               <hi>The Opinion of two eminent Parliament-Men, juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the lawfulneſs of taking the Oaths of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to King</hi> William <hi>and Queen</hi> Mary.</head>
            <p n="1">I. FIdelity and Allegiance ſworn to the King, is only a Fidelity and Obedience as it is due to him by the Law of the Land; for were that Faith and Allegiance more than what the Law requires, we ſhould ſwear our ſelves Slaves, and the King Abſolute; whereas by the Law we are free, notwithſtanding theſe Oaths.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:41592:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> II. When therefore by the Law Fidelity and Allegiance ceaſeth, then our ſworn Allegiance ceaſeth: for if Allegiance might be due by the Oath to one Perſon, whilſt by the Law it ceaſeth to him and becomes due to another Perſon, the Oath then would oblige Men to tranſgreſs the Law, and become Traytors and Rebels, whereas the Oath is part of the Law, and therefore ought to be ſo interpreted as may conſiſt with it.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Fidelity and Allegiance are due by the Law to King <hi>William,</hi> and not to King <hi>James:</hi> for the Statute of 25 of <hi>Edward</hi> 3<hi>d,</hi> which defined all Treaſons againſt the King, and is the only Statute to that purpoſe; now that Statute, by the King, underſtands not only a King <hi>de jure,</hi> but alſo a King <hi>de facto,</hi> tho not <hi>de jure,</hi> againſt whom thoſe Treaſons Lie: whence the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hales,</hi> in his Pleas of the Crown, <hi>p.</hi> 12. diſcourſing of that Statute, tells us, that a King <hi>de facto,</hi> and not <hi>de jure,</hi> is a King within that Act, and that Treaſon againſt him is Puniſhable, tho the Right Heir get the Crown: and that this hath been the common Senſe of the Law, Sir <hi>R. S.</hi> (upon application to him about it) hath aſſured us. And according to another Statute, 11 <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>ch.</hi> 1. It is declared Treaſon to be in Arms againſt a King <hi>de facto,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Richard</hi> the 3<hi>d</hi> was, tho it was in behalf of a King <hi>de jure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then by the Law of the Land, all things are Treaſon againſt King <hi>William,</hi> which have been Treaſon againſt former Kings, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſame Fidelity, Obedience and Allegiance, which was due to them, is due to him, and by Conſequence may be Sworn to him by the Law of the Land.</p>
            <p>Allegiance and Protection are always Mutual, and therefore when King <hi>James</hi> ceaſed to Protect us, we ceaſed to owe him Allegiance by the Law of the Land; and when King <hi>William</hi> began to Protect us we began our Allegiance to him.</p>
            <p>Theſe Conſiderations, are in our Opinion, ſufficient to remove the Grand Scruple about the Oaths. If the diſſatisfied Party accuſe the Convention, for making the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> King, it is not my Duty to judge thoſe above me, therefore I ſhall only ſay that if they have done ill, <hi>Quod fieri non debuit factum valot;</hi> and they of the Clergy ought not to cenſure their Superiours, but obey according to the Law and Doctrine of Paſſive Obedience.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:41592:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
